<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation against those that doeth innouate, alter or leaue doune any rite or ceremonie in the Church, of their priuate aucthoritie: and against them which preacheth without licence, set furth the .vj. daie of Februarij, in the seconde yere of the Kynges Maiesties most gracious reigne</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1548-02-06</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1547-1553 : Edward VI)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844981</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844981</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9843)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 10:26, 152:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation against those that doeth innouate, alter or leaue doune any rite or ceremonie in the Church, of their priuate aucthoritie: and against them which preacheth without licence, set furth the .vj. daie of Februarij, in the seconde yere of the Kynges Maiesties most gracious reigne</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1548-02-06</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1547-1553 : Edward VI)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Richardi Graftoni regij impressoris. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Society of Antiquaries.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 10 and 152 (Society of Antiquaries copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Edward VI, 1447-1553 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:9843:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>¶ A Proclamacion againſt thoſe that doeth innouate, alter or leaue doune any Rite or Ceremonie in the Church, of their priuate aucthoritie: and aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt them whiche preacheth without licence, ſet furth <date>the .vj. daie of Februarij, in the ſeconde yere of the Kynges Maieſties moſte gracious reigne.</date>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He kyngnes highnes by the aduiſe of his moſte entier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued Vncle, the Duke of Somerſette, Gouernor of his moſte royall perſone, and Protector of all his Realmes, Dominions and Subiectes, and others of his Counſaill: Conſideryng nothyng ſo muche, to tende to the diſquietyng of his realme, as diuerſitie of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and varietie of Rites and Ceremonies, concernyng Religion and worſhippyng of almightie God, and therefore ſtudiyng all the waies &amp; meanes, whiche can be to directe this Churche and the Cure, committed to his highnes, in one and moſte true doctrine, Rite and Vſage: Yet is aduertiſed that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain priuate Curates, Preachers, and other laye men, contrary to their bounden dueties of obedience, doth raſhely attempte of their awne and ſinguler witte and mynde, in ſome Pariſhe Churches and otherwiſe, not onely to perſwade the people, from the olde and accuſtomed Rites and Ceremonies, but alſo theimſelf bryngeth in newe and ſtraunge orders, euery one in their Churche, accordyng to their phantaſies: The whiche as it is an euident token of pride and arrogancie, ſo it tendeth bothe to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and diſordre, and alſo to the high diſpleaſure of almightie God, who loueth nothyng ſo muche as ordre and obedience: Wherefore his Maieſtie ſtraightly chargeth and commaundeth, that no maner perſone, of what eſtate, ordre, or degree ſo euer he be, of his priuate mynde, will or phantaſie, do omitte, leaue doune, chaunge, alter or innouate any ordre, Rite or Ceremonie, commonly vſed and frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Churche of Englande, and not commaunded to bee left doune at any tyme, in the reigne of our late ſouereigne lorde his highnes father other then ſuche as his highnes, by the aduiſe aforeſaied, by his maieſties viſitours, Iniunccions, Statutes or Proclamacions, hath already or hereafter ſhall commaunde, to be omitted, left, innouated, or chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged: But that thei be obſerued after that ſort, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thei wer accuſtomed, or els now ſithe preſcribed, by the aucthoritie of his maieſtie, and by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aforeſaied, vpon pain that whoſoeuer ſhall offende, contrary to this Proclamacion, ſhall incurre his highnes indignacion, and ſuffre impriſonment, and other greuous puniſhementes, at his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties wil and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> to the intente that raſhe and ſedicious Preachers, ſhould not abuſe his highnes people, it is his Maieſties pleaſure, that whoſoeuer ſhall take vpon hym to preache openly, in any parriſhe Churche, Chapell, or any other open place, other then thoſe, whiche be licenſed by the kynges maieſtie, or his highnes Viſitours, the Archebiſhoppe of Canterbury, or the Biſhoppe of the Dioceſe where he doth preache: Excepte it bee the Biſhop, Perſone, Vicar, Deane, Warden, or Prouoſt, in his or their awne Cure, ſhalbe furthwith vpon ſuche attempt and preachyng, contrary to this Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, committed to priſone, and there remain vntill ſuche tyme, as his maieſtie by the aduiſe aforeſaid, hath taken ordre for the further puniſhment of the ſame. And that the premiſſes ſhould bee more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely and diligently doen and performed, his highnes geueth ſtraightly in commaundement, to al Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace, Maiours, Shiriefes, Conſtables, hed Borrowes, Churche, Wardens, and all other his Maieſties Officers and Miniſters, and rulers of Tounes, Parriſhes, and Hamlettes: That thei be diligent and attendaunt, to the true and faithfull excucion of this Proclamacion, and euery parte thereof, according to thintent, purport and effecte of the ſame. And that thei of their procedynges here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (or if any offender be) after thei haue commited the ſame to priſon, do certifie his highnes, the lorde Protector, or his maieſties Counſaill, with all ſpede thereof accordyngly: as thei tender his maieſties pleaſure, the wealth of the realme, and will aunſwere to the contrary, at their vttermoſt perilles.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Kyng.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Excuſum Londini, in aedibus Richard Graftoni Regij Impreſsoris.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
